<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>dinogalactic - misc</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.dinogalactic.com/</id><updated>2024-02-19T06:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>My pentesting tenets</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/my-pentesting-tenets.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-19T06:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-19T06:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2024-02-19:/my-pentesting-tenets.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I follow a method built on a few tenets. I didn't set out to make this pseudo-buddhist, but it turned out a little bit like that. These are the things that help me so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try the attack. Don't assume, even if it seems impossible or incredibly stupid that an …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I follow a method built on a few tenets. I didn't set out to make this pseudo-buddhist, but it turned out a little bit like that. These are the things that help me so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try the attack. Don't assume, even if it seems impossible or incredibly stupid that an attack would work. Remember that the early phone phreakers thought it was impossible that whistling 2600Hz could get them a free phone call.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it isn't written down, it didn't happen. This goes for everything in your life, not just pentesting, but it applies doubly so for pentesting. Attack ideas, attack attempts - everything you thought and tried - needs to be written down. Remember this from Cliff Stoll and The Cuckoo's egg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Magic isn't real. Even if it seems hackers sometimes communicate on a direct spiritual channel with computers and can sense vulnerabilities before touching the keyboard, every fascinating hack is the result of grueling trial and error, and every slick talk at DEFCON hides literally years of trying shit to see if it worked. For every successful attack, there are hundreds of failed attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chop wood; carry water. Give yourself over to the method, accept what it gives back, and ask for nothing more. Getting frustrated, getting ahead of yourself, and daydreaming about how this attack will definitely work and will definitely secure you the ultimate prize are all symptoms of not listening to this tenet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go step by step. Let your notes guide you to the next step. A knitter creates a beautiful garment out of a single length of wool one stitch at a time. Focus on the next step before you look back and see what you have made, or look forward to what you haven't. Looking forward or backward will make you sad that you haven't done enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="security"></category></entry><entry><title>You should use boto3 paginators</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/you-should-use-boto3-paginators.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-04T06:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-04T06:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2021-03-04:/you-should-use-boto3-paginators.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to point out that you may want to refactor your boto code, depending
on how much time you have, to use a paginator rather than handling the
nextToken from the AWS API yourself. This will return an API response on each
iteration over the paginator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's an example …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to point out that you may want to refactor your boto code, depending
on how much time you have, to use a paginator rather than handling the
nextToken from the AWS API yourself. This will return an API response on each
iteration over the paginator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's an example run against my personal AWS account, which only has one page of CFN stacks unfortunately:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite" style="background: #f0f3f3"&gt;&lt;pre style="line-height: 125%"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;In [&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;]: &lt;span style="color: #006699; font-weight: bold"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: #00CCFF; font-weight: bold"&gt;boto3&lt;/span&gt;                                                                                                                                                                         
In [&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;]: boto3&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;client(&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;cloudformation&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;)                                                                                                                                                       
Out[&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;]: &lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;botocore&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;client&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;CloudFormation at &lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;0x7f9abc2fbaf0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
In [&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;]: cfn_client &lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; boto3&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;client(&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;cloudformation&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;)                                                                                                                                          
In [&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;]: cfn_client&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;can_paginate(&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;describe_stacks&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style="color: #0099FF; font-style: italic"&gt;# Figure out if you can paginate your desired cfn_client command before using this technique                                                                                                                                            &lt;/span&gt;
Out[&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;]: &lt;span style="color: #006699; font-weight: bold"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;
In [&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;]: paginator &lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; cfn_client&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;get_paginator(&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;describe_stacks&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;)                                                                                                                              
In [&lt;span style="color: #FF6600"&gt;29&lt;/span&gt;]: &lt;span style="color: #006699; font-weight: bold"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; resp &lt;span style="color: #000000; font-weight: bold"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; paginator&lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;paginate(): &lt;span style="color: #0099FF; font-style: italic"&gt;# You can also pass in any keyword args that cfn_client.describe_stacks() would take here, like paginator.paginate(StackName=&amp;#39;blahblahblah&amp;#39;) &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;:     &lt;span style="color: #336666"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;([stack[&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;StackName&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;] &lt;span style="color: #006699; font-weight: bold"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; stack &lt;span style="color: #000000; font-weight: bold"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; resp[&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;Stacks&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;]]) 
    &lt;span style="color: #555555"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;: 
[&lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;chickenpi-app-epp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;gg-service-role&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;chickenpi-pl-epp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;cfn-leaprog-trail&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;aws-cloud9-Python-Development-Environment-f5f7b7b71b124224a4472c8768327a97&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="color: #CC3300"&gt;&amp;#39;aws-sam-cli-managed-default&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are the boto3 &lt;a href="https://boto3.amazonaws.com/v1/documentation/api/latest/guide/paginators.html"&gt;pagination docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="aws"></category></entry><entry><title>Powering a Ham Radio with a Laptop Battery</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/powering-a-ham-radio-with-a-laptop-battery.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-05T22:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-05T22:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2020-05-05:/powering-a-ham-radio-with-a-laptop-battery.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had &lt;a href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/debugging-an-inteference-problem-on-my-ubitx-v6.html"&gt;some bad luck with a cheap 12V power supply&lt;/a&gt; with my &lt;a href="https://www.hfsignals.com/index.php/ubitx-v6/"&gt;uBitx v6&lt;/a&gt;. In short, the supply was extremely noisy across all the RF bands I wanted to use. I had said in that other post that I would buy a better power supply suitable for RF …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had &lt;a href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/debugging-an-inteference-problem-on-my-ubitx-v6.html"&gt;some bad luck with a cheap 12V power supply&lt;/a&gt; with my &lt;a href="https://www.hfsignals.com/index.php/ubitx-v6/"&gt;uBitx v6&lt;/a&gt;. In short, the supply was extremely noisy across all the RF bands I wanted to use. I had said in that other post that I would buy a better power supply suitable for RF, but I don't believe you should do that when you can hack something together using parts you already have, especially when just starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I poached the working Lithium Ion battery from the very Dell Lattitude E5540 laptop that I'm writing this on, and everything is working perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how I did that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Find a decent approximation of the Laptop's pinout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="https://www.laptop-junction.com/toast/content/inside-dell-d610-battery-connector-pinout-and-signal-timing"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; I found the basic info I needed to hook up to my Laptop battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, I found this info that would work if my battery pinout wasn't too different from the one in the picture. Mine had 9 pins, just like the one on that site, so chances were decent the pinout was the same or similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3 most important facts were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the left and rightmost two pairs of pins need to be shorted as two pairs (one short on each side, so the four pins effectively become two wires)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one of the pairs is ground (-), and the other pair is (+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one of the pins in the middle needs to be shorted to ground &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wire the battery up to a breadboard and onto the radio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just had to figure out which pin on my battery had to be shorted to ground to turn the battery on, since I got no voltage by simple shorting the pairs of pins on the (+) and (-) sides. Finally, I realized from the above site's pin list that my pin 6 might be something called &lt;code&gt;SYSPRES&lt;/code&gt;, probably meaning &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM PRESENT&lt;/code&gt;, or in human terms "This battery is not being shorted accidentally in someone's purse by their earrings - it's plugged into a laptop." Once I connected pin 6 to ground, I got a little over 12V out between (+) and (-). For safety, I added a toggle switch between pin 6 and ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img alt="Annotated drawing of the battery wireup job I did." src="https://www.dinogalactic.com/images/annotated_dell_laptop_battery.jpg" /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The radio turned on with zero noise - no loud helicopter blade sounds.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Turn it on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="My first HF station, a uBitx v6, powered by the battery power source I hacked together." src="https://www.dinogalactic.com/images/first_hf_station.jpg" /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Here it is, turned on. Yes, right now my uBitx is in a cardboard box. Stay tuned for a future project where it might live in a nice wooden box.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Profit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will keep going with this setup as long as I can. It's working, is noiseless, is free for me, and since I don't take my laptop anywhere really, is not inconvenient yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="ubitx"></category><category term="amateur radio"></category><category term="ham radio"></category></entry><entry><title>Debugging an Inteference Problem on My uBitx v6</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/debugging-an-inteference-problem-on-my-ubitx-v6.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-22T06:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T06:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2020-03-22:/debugging-an-inteference-problem-on-my-ubitx-v6.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got my uBitx v6 recently from
&lt;a href="https://www.hfsignals.com/index.php/ubitx-v6/"&gt;hfsignals&lt;/a&gt; and hooked it up to
a 20m/40m trapped dipole from &lt;a href="http://qrpkits.com/dualbanddipole.html"&gt;Pacific
Antenna&lt;/a&gt;, mounted about 30 ft off the
ground as an inverted vee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I've made no contacts and been able to hear only one half of an SSB
conversation …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got my uBitx v6 recently from
&lt;a href="https://www.hfsignals.com/index.php/ubitx-v6/"&gt;hfsignals&lt;/a&gt; and hooked it up to
a 20m/40m trapped dipole from &lt;a href="http://qrpkits.com/dualbanddipole.html"&gt;Pacific
Antenna&lt;/a&gt;, mounted about 30 ft off the
ground as an inverted vee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I've made no contacts and been able to hear only one half of an SSB
conversation that sounded like it was coming from somewhere near me in
Virginia. I've been able to hear some digital modes and very small bursts (a
couple of letters) of CW on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately everywhere I tune on my radio sounds like intense static garbage
- a problem I'm assuming for now is QRM that can be removed. In other words, I
don't think it's coming from inside the radio. (I have a couple of reasons for
this - mainly that when I unplug the antenna or put a large resistive load on
the antenna connector, the static is gone.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Symptoms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manifests as a crackly static&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occurs across all bands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has so far only allowed geographically close reception (possibly indicating
  desensitization of signals that aren't extremely strong, or maybe my antenna
  is accidentally an NVIS antenna?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gets much, much more aggressive (louder) as I go down in frequency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does not improve when all devices in the house are off except the radio's
  switching 12V power supply - I haven't yet tried on batteries alone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Possible causes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFI from the 12V switching power supply I got on
  &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01461MOGQ/"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFI from a neighbor's electronic device(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power line interference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some form of coupling or common mode current (I'm way out of my depth here in
  terms of understanding, but my station is ungrounded and I am not using a
  balun on my inverted vee)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some problem caused by an incorrectly installed BNC connector on my coax
  cable. I feel pretty OK with my stripping and crimping job, but these were a
  couple of the first BNC connectors I ever crimped onto the end of a coax
  cable, so maybe I caused some problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Video of interference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a video with audio of the interference. I switch across the bands to
show that the interference is extremely wide banded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dR2Hp0X5kww"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dR2Hp0X5kww&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting detail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I connect an alligator clip from a 160 foot piece of RG8X cable I have lying
in a coil nearby, the static gets much more intense. Not sure if this could be
a clue to what the problem is, but if so, I have no idea how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How I Fixed It&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't yet, but I did figure out what was causing the problem. I realized
that the last step to rule out my own house's devices from the list of possible
causes was to run the ubitx on battery power with all my home power turned off.
I didn't have a 12V battery or battery pack, so I wired one up using 8 alkaline AA batteries I had lying around, and voila - no
static whatsoever. Interestingly after play with the radio for a while, I did
notice that the cheap LED grow lights I use for my tomatoes and peppers create
strong interference, but they're close to the radio and easy to turn off
temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After eliminating the RFI, I immediately heard the Russian station &lt;a href="https://www.qrz.com/db/R2OA"&gt;R2OA&lt;/a&gt; coming through on 14.203 MHz SSB during the &lt;a href="http://www.rdxc.org/asp/pages/rulesg.asp"&gt;Russian DX contest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, some AAs from the store are going to last less than an hour. My long-term solution to the switching power supply issue is to buy one made for radio use, like &lt;a href="https://www.mfjenterprises.com/Product.php?productid=MFJ-4225MV"&gt;this one by MFJ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="ubitx"></category><category term="amateur radio"></category><category term="ham radio"></category></entry><entry><title>What Have I Actually Done at My Current Job?</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/what-have-i-actually-done-at-my-current-job.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-26T06:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-26T06:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2019-11-26:/what-have-i-actually-done-at-my-current-job.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This quite out of date since it was last updated in 2019. I have worn
many different hats since then. Still, I like keeping this stuff up here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I sat down to work on my resume any day but today, I would probably forget
that I was the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This quite out of date since it was last updated in 2019. I have worn
many different hats since then. Still, I like keeping this stuff up here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I sat down to work on my resume any day but today, I would probably forget
that I was the one who managed much of our development team's Omniture
integrations at Truth Initiative Innovations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not create a long-lived, long-updated post that lists out these lesser
remembered things, and maybe even some of the morer remembered things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it's time to sit down in front of the resume etching machine, I will be ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On 10-14-2020, my dev lead/acting supervisor said:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for handling the deploy stuff and the details for [client]
You very consistently handle this sort of “getting the end of a project
wrangled and live” well, and it’s been a huge load off knowing you have it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I managed the Omniture Integrations at Truth Initiative Innovations. This
  includes classifying variables, being the person who knows the stuff about
  how Omniture works on the team (e.g. I was one of the two people who could
  remind people what evars and sprops were), and I'd take point on
  troubleshooting wiley Omniture bugs (like - why wasn't some registration data
  getting associated with a "person" in Jive, yet other stuff apparently was?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At one point, I created a webhook-based system to receive and report page view
    events to external partners who were paying for that data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a long while, our servers were locking up because of blocking connections
  to our centralized (cloud) logging provider, and when the server came back
  online (usually after a hard reboot through the console at the datacenter),
  we would have lost all logs during that period. I fixed this by investigating
  our rsyslog config and improving it to not drop these messages when the
  logging provider was unavailable, and also to not block incoming syslog
  messages during this period, thus avoiding server lockups altogether. We went
  from "Oh my god we had better restart rsyslog soon or the server will crash"
  to "Oh look, we got an alert that rsyslog is experiencing connection
  problems. It will eventually come back online and send our logs to the
  logging provider." Because of this blocking and a less than great &lt;code&gt;rsyslog&lt;/code&gt;
  configuration, our local syslog server would block applications' socket
  connections on the &lt;code&gt;/dev/log&lt;/code&gt; socket, and since many important processes
  (such as &lt;code&gt;sshd&lt;/code&gt;!) submitted syslog messages at this location, many processes
  on the server locked up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created an import mechanism for semi-technical business personnel to compose
  SMS text message conversations. This involves composing a series of messages,
  recognized regexes, responses, and API integrations as an artifact that can
  be uploaded to multiple environments and tested before going to production.
  This was an improvement from the method of filling out HTML forms for each
  message and saving them in an instance/environment's DB state with no easy
  way to replicate this in other environments. In short, I created an artifact
  format for non-developers to use as a better interface for creating text
  message conversations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used a couple of Kibana cloud solutions daily to debug production issues and
  alert on them. Also often led the charge to seriously log as much as
  humanly/computerly possible in our apps to allow future observability. I
  wanted people to be able to find the exact code line and related data (db
  rows, etc.) needed to debug an issue, just by looking at the error log.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built development, staging, and production, as well as CI, infrastructure on
  AWS EC2/RDS with Ansible and Jenkins as well as Heroku and Heroku CI. Also
  built development infra on Docker (with and without Docker Compose) and
  Vagrant with Ansible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architected a move from managed multi-server, multi-app VPS hosting to AWS,
  adding load balancing into the mix for the first time for the application.
  Automated all AWS infrastructure creation/management in Ansible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designed a test interface for message library admins to simulate user
  experiences so they could gain confidence that their text messaging programs
  would work as expected for various users up to 90 days in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="resume"></category><category term="evergreen"></category></entry><entry><title>Introducing My 5-year Old to Computers Using a Raspberry Pi</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/introducing-my-5-year-old-to-computers-using-a-raspberry-pi.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-18T06:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T06:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2019-11-18:/introducing-my-5-year-old-to-computers-using-a-raspberry-pi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My 5-year-old told me last night,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm five now, so I should have a 'puter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we got started with a Raspberry Pi. She had so many problems getting started
that I hadn't anticipated, and since I was so shocked by these, I wanted to
write down the things I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My 5-year-old told me last night,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm five now, so I should have a 'puter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we got started with a Raspberry Pi. She had so many problems getting started
that I hadn't anticipated, and since I was so shocked by these, I wanted to
write down the things I learned from giving our first "computer lesson."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Kids at this age can't control a high-sensitivity mouse.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn the sensitivity &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Maybe giant, bright screens aren't great right before bed.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They aren't good for my sleep, so why would they be for hers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Jamming on the keyboard is fun, but pointless.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's probably something they'll want to do (because they sees you do it all the
time!), but it's potentially destructive (it is possible to type some junk that
messes up your intended work together), and at the very least mashing the
keyboard doesn't work toward some better goal. Next time I'll better resist the
urge to let her do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice with your tech setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This really goes for any technical presentation or training, but check your
software and hardware setup and make sure it's as rock solid as you can make it
before you start. Murphy's Law still applies, but maybe you'll avoid some lag
time at the outset. My biggest mistake was not even digging through storage
boxes to dig out my Raspberry Pis before we started. As a result, we first
plugged in the Raspberry Pi B because it was the only one I could find in my
frantic search. But it didn't work. Haven't investigated why. Then the
Raspberry Pi 2 I subsequently dug out was set up as an Arch Pi box with no X
display, and it had a password I couldn't remember. By the time we got the
Raspberry Pi 3 Model B that I finally found, I wasted valuable attention on
stuff that probably only confused her. I should've just gotten the stuff out
and set it up once ahead of time to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set expectations for computer usage rules and time limits &lt;em&gt;early&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should've set limits around computer usage from the first moment. In general,
explaining expectations and setting limits for her early and in a direct manner
helps her deal with them, but I didn't do that this time. While things turned
out OK, I realized today that she thought she could use the computer whenever
she wanted, and even without me. We have strict rules around screen time, but
up till now that has only applied to television time, since she hadn't used a
computer before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice getting into their naive mindset&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, again, astonishing how little she knows about computers. It shouldn't
be, but I don't spend much time teaching anymore, and I have to work harder to
imagine/remember what it was like not to know, for instance, what a mouse is.
We operate at &lt;em&gt;such&lt;/em&gt; a high level compared to her, and while I've taught in the
past and know this is part of good teaching, I had a lot of trouble changing my
expectations and really meeting where she was rather than where I expected her
to be. For instance, I had set a goal for her to double click an icon on the
desktop (to myself - I didn't tell her I expected her to be able to do this) as
the big action in our ~hour of time together, but I had completely overlooked
the fact that she didn't even know the mouse has two buttons (right and left
clicking), or that the scroll wheel isn't always useful, or that &lt;em&gt;moving the
mouse forward on the desk moves it up on the screen&lt;/em&gt;. When I asked her to move
her cursor to a location on the screen, she began picking up the mouse from the
desk to move it up to the screen. I have a lot to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we mostly practiced mouse usage after plugging in the cords. I wouldn't trade it for anything.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="kids"></category><category term="parenting"></category><category term="linux"></category><category term="raspi"></category></entry><entry><title>Smart things to say when a production bug arises in software development</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/smart-things-to-say-when-a-production-bug-arises-in-software-development.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-10T06:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-10T06:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2019-06-10:/smart-things-to-say-when-a-production-bug-arises-in-software-development.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I noticed an issue that was affecting production. Doesn't matter the issue, I don't think, but my supervisor asked some good questions, so I figured I'd document them. This helps me remember what I should do to be a better leader in emergent situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren't direct quotes, just …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I noticed an issue that was affecting production. Doesn't matter the issue, I don't think, but my supervisor asked some good questions, so I figured I'd document them. This helps me remember what I should do to be a better leader in emergent situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren't direct quotes, just summaries of the things he wanted to figure out to help him prioritize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does this relate to some previous or ongoing issue that we know about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If so, what do I need to know about it that others on the team already know?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does this affect users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we know how many users are affected, or can we find out?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no one has reproduced the issue, could someone make a ticket and spend some short amount of time trying to reproduce it (up to 90 minutes)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we can reproduce it, are there estimates of difficulty on a fix?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we were going to deploy it, would anything special be required in that deploy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="software development"></category><category term="project management"></category></entry><entry><title>init</title><link href="https://www.dinogalactic.com/init.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-22T02:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-22T02:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Eddie Peters</name></author><id>tag:www.dinogalactic.com,2019-05-22:/init.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First ever post on website.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Initial.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category></entry></feed>